There is a הלכה Halacha that we find in
the גמרא Gemara in מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbos that a
person is not allowed to read by
the light of an oil lamp on
שבת. Shabbos. The reason the חכמים Chachamim gave for this is a
גזירה gezeirah of שמא יטה, shema yiteh, that perhaps a
person will forget it is שבת Shabbos and
they will tilt the lamp in order
to bring the oil closer to the
wick, which would be a violation of
the מלאכה melacha of מבעיר. mavir. Now, the question
is, does this הלכה Halacha apply nowadays when
we have electric lights? Most פוסקים poskim say
that it does not apply because there
is no way to tilt the lamp
to make the light stronger in the
same way, and also because we are
so used to electric lights that we
do not even think about it. However,
some are מחמיר machmir and say that one
should still be careful. Another important concept
is מוקצה. Muktzeh. If a candle was lit
at the time of בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, which
is the twilight period between Friday and
שבת, Shabbos, it becomes מוקצה Muktzeh for the entire
day. This is because of the principle
of מיגו דאיתקצאי לבין השמשות איתקצאי לכולי
יומא. migo d'itaktzai l'bein hashmashos itaktzai l'kuly yoma. Even if the candle
goes out in the middle of the
night, you still cannot move the candlestick
because it was a בסיס לדבר האסור,
basis l'davar hassur, a base for a
forbidden object, at the onset of the
holy day. This is the הלכה Halacha that
we learn in the סוגיא sugya of the
laws of שבת. Shabbos. In the last משנה
Mishnah at the bottom of the previous
דף Daf on דף מ"ו Daf Mem-Vav עמוד ב', Amud Bet, the
משנה Mishnah said הזהב קונה את הכסף והכסף
אינו קונה את הזהב, HaZahav koneh et haKesef vehaKesef eino koneh et
haZahav, gold acquires silver, but silver does
not acquire gold. This is because according
to the משנה Mishnah gold is considered פירא, Peira, a commodity, and
silver is considered מטבע, Matbeia, currency. The rule of קניינים Kinyanim is
that the commodity acquires the currency. If you pull the commodity, the
currency is acquired to the seller wherever it is. But if you
pull the currency, the commodity is not acquired to the buyer until
the buyer performs משיכה Meshichah on the commodity. The גמרא Gemara on
דף מ"ז Daf Mem-Zayin עמוד א' Amud Aleph asks why gold is
considered the commodity. We see a מחלוקת Machloket between רב Rav and
לוי Levi regarding this. One says gold is מטבע Matbeia because it
is more valuable, and the other says silver is מטבע Matbeia because
it is more common. The הלכה Halacha follows the view that silver
is the currency. We also discuss that מדאורייתא, Mi-de'Oraita, biblical law, מעות
קונות, Maot konot, money is a valid קניין. Kinyan. However, the חכמים
Chachamim made a תקנה Takanah that one must perform משיכה. Meshichah. This
was done to protect the buyer in case of a fire, a
concept known as נשרפו פירותיך בעלייה. Nisrefu peirotecha ba'aliyah. If the seller
still bears responsibility, he will do more to save the goods. But
if a person retracts after giving money, the בית דין Beit Din
subjects him to the curse of מי שפרע, Mi ShePara, stating that
the One who punished the generations of the flood and the dispersion
will punish him for not keeping his word. In the גמרא Gemara
in מסכת תענית, Maseches Taanis, the משנה Mishnah discusses the concept of
תענית ציבור. taanis tzibur. When there is a צרה tzarah in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, such as a drought, the בית דין Beis Din
would declare a series of fasts. During these times, the people would
gather in the רחובה של עיר, rechovah shel ir, the city square,
and the זקן zaken would deliver words of התעוררות hissorerus to inspire
the community to perform תשובה. teshuvah. They would bring out the ארון
aron and place אפר eifer on it to show their distress and
הכנעה hachna'ah before השם. Hashem. The גמרא Gemara emphasizes that it is
not the שק sak or the תענית taanis itself that brings forgiveness,
but rather the תיקון המעשים, tikun hama'asim, the improvement of one's actions.
As it says regarding the people of נינוה, Nineveh, the פסוק posuk
does not say that אלוקים Elokim saw their fasting, but rather וירא
אלוקים את מעשיהם, vayar Elokim es ma'aseihem, that He saw their deeds.
This teaches us that the main goal of any תענית taanis is
to lead us toward a genuine חזרה בתשובה. chazara b'teshuvah. We must
look into our behaviors and ensure we are acting with appropriate בין
אדם לחברו bein adam l'chavero and בין אדם למקום. bein adam l'makom.
Through this, we merit the רחמים rachamim of the בורא עולם Borei
Olam and the ultimate גאולה שלימה Geulah Sheleimah speedily in our days.
אמן. Amen. So says רבא, Rava, according to רב Rav who says
that even a סוכה Sukkah which is higher than twenty אמות amos
can be valid if you have the דפנות defanos reaching up to
the סכך, sechach, so why over here by the bed do you
need it to be עשרה טפחים? asara tefachim? Even if the bed
was less than עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, it should already be considered
an אהל. ohel. Because according to רב, Rav, you don't need a
space of עשרה טפחים asara tefachim to be considered an אהל. ohel.
And the גמרא Gemara answers: אמר לך רב, Amar lach Rav, רב
Rav could say to you: התם דפנות לאהל עבידי, Hasam defanos leohel
avidi, over there by the סוכה, Sukkah, the דפנות defanos are made
for the sake of the אהל. ohel. הכא כרעי המיטה לאו לאהל
עבידי, Hacha karayei hamita lav leohel avidi, but here, the legs of
the bed are not made for the sake of an אהל. ohel.
Since they're not made for the sake of an אהל, ohel, they
only become an אהל ohel if they are at least
עשרה טפחים asara tefachim high. Because once they reach
עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, it's considered an important enough
space to be an אהל ohel regardless of
what it was made for. But if
it's less than עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, and it
wasn't made to be an אהל, ohel, then
it's not considered an אהל. ohel. And therefore,
it would not be a חציצה, chatzitzah, and
you would fulfill your obligation. This is how רב Rav would answer
the question of רבא Rava from the משנה Mishna later on. We
have a custom that we begin every month by reciting a specific
prayer on the Sabbath before the beginning of the new month. We
ask God to bless the new month, to grant us a month
of life and of peace, a month of health and of prosperity.
We call this prayer ברכת החודש. Birkat HaChodesh. But there is one
month in the year when we do not recite this prayer on
the Sabbath before the month begins, and that is the month of
תשרי. Tishrei. The Sabbath before ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, we do not
bless the new month. Why is that? After all, ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah is ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It is
the first day of the new month
of תשרי. Tishrei. Why is it that the
month of תשרי Tishrei is treated differently? The
רבי, Rebbe, Rabbi Menachem Mendel of Rymanov, explains
that the reason we do not bless
the month of תשרי Tishrei is because the
entire preceding month, the month of אלול,
Elul, is one long blessing for the
month of תשרי. Tishrei. The month of אלול
Elul is a month of preparation. It
is a month of introspection. It is
a month of תשובה. Teshuva. And through the
work that we do during the month
of אלול, Elul, we provide the blessing for
the coming year. We are now in
the midst of these days of אלול.
Elul. These are days that are meant
for reflection. We look back at the
year that has passed. We think about
the choices we've made, the actions we've
taken, and the words we've spoken. And
we ask ourselves, where can we improve?
How can we grow? How can we
become closer to the person that we
truly want to be? This is the
essence of תשובה. Teshuva. Often translated as repentance,
תשובה Teshuva really means return. It's a return
to our true selves. It's a return
to our relationship with God. The רמב"ם
Rambam teaches us that תשובה Teshuva involves several
steps: וידוי, Viduy, verbalizing our mistakes; חרטה, Charata, feeling
sincere regret; and קבלה על העתיד, Kabbalah al ha-atid, making
a firm commitment to do better in
the future. But the goal is not
just to fix the past. The goal
is to transform ourselves for the future.
As we move closer to ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, let us
take advantage of these final days of
אלול. Elul. Let us use this time to
truly bless the coming year through our
own efforts and our own growth. May
we all be blessed with a כתיבה
וחתימה טובה, Ketiva V'Chatima Tova, to be inscribed and sealed
in the book of life for a
good, healthy, and meaningful new year. The
נשמה neshama comes from high up specifically to
fix up. We find that there's people
that are doing certain מצוות mitzvos more than
others and that's their תיקון. tikkun. A person
has to know that's why you're here,
to fix something. But people come with
a specific תיקון tikkun into this world for
something. Like the האר"י הקדוש Arizal HaKadosh says that
there's certain things, certain מצוות mitzvos that we
find it easier, not easier, but we
find that we have to do it
more than other people. We're very careful
on those specific מצוות. mitzvos. That is probably
your תיקון. tikkun. A person has to work
on that תיקון. tikkun. Or sometimes you find something that's difficult for
you to do, that's also something that you have to fix up.
It's either a love for the מצוה mitzvah or difficulty with the
מצוה. mitzvah. And the question is, why do we have this constant
battle? Why do we have to have this battle? The חובת הלבבות
Chovos HaLevavos in שער הבחינה, Sha'ar HaBechina, רבינו בחיי, Rabbeinu Bachya, he
says that the נשמה neshama comes from a very high place. It's
like royalty. It's like a king. It's like a queen. The נשמה
neshama is a very high thing. But when it's put in the
גוף, guf, it's put in a prison. It's put in something that's
very low, very physical, very coarse. And the גוף guf wants the
physical. The גוף guf wants the mundane. The נשמה neshama wants the
spiritual. So there's a constant battle between the נשמה neshama and the
גוף. guf. And the goal of a person in this world is
to make the גוף guf subservient to the נשמה. neshama. To make
the physical subservient to the spiritual. That is the work of a
person in this world. And that's why we have this battle. And
the harder the battle, the more reward a person gets. לפום צערא
אגרא. Lefum tza'ara agra. According to the pain, that is the reward.
Hello everybody. Today we are going to learn a bit from the
פרשה. parsha. This week is פרשת וירא. parshat Vayera. In the beginning
of the פרשה parsha it says וירא אליו ה׳. Vayera Elav Hashem.
רש״י Rashi explains that it was the third day after the ברית
מילה brit milah of אברהם אבינו. Avraham Avinu. Even though it was
כחום היום, k'chom hayom, אברהם Avraham was looking for guests for הכנסת
אורחים. hachnasat orchim. When the three מלאכים malachim came, he ran to
greet them. This teaches us the importance of חסד. chesed. The גמרא
gemara in מסכת שבת masechet Shabbat says גדולה הכנסת אורחים מקבלת פני
השכינה. gedolah hachnasat orchim mi'kabalat pnei hashechina. May we all be זוכה
zoche to do more מצוות. mitzvot. שבת שלום. shabbat shalom. The fifth
chapter of מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbos, פרק במה בהמה, Perek Bameh Behemah,
with what may an animal go out on שבת? Shabbos? במה בהמה
יוצאה ובמה אינה יוצאה. Bameh behemah yotzeh u-vameh einah yotzeh. With what
may an animal go out and with what may it not go
out? יוצא הגמל באפסנא. yotzeh ha-gamal be-afsana. A camel may go out
with a halter. ונאקה בחטם, ve-nakah be-chotem, and a dromedary with a
nose ring. ולובדקיס בפרומביא, ve-luvdekis be-farumbiya, and a Libyan donkey with a
bit. וסוס בשיר, ve-sus be-shir, and a horse with a chain. וכל
בעלי השיר יוצאים בשיר ונמשכים בשיר. ve-chol ba'alei ha-shir yotze'im be-shir ve-nimshachim
be-shir. And all animals that have chains go out with a chain
and are led by the chain. ומזין עליהן וטובלין במקומן. u-mazin aleihen
ve-tovlin bi-mekoman. One may sprinkle on them or immerse them in their
places if they become טמא. tamei. This refers to the metal chains
which are susceptible to טומאה tumah because they are considered a כלי.
kli. But the משנה Mishna says you can dip them in a
מקוה mikvah while they are still on the animal. The reason we
are concerned with what the animal is wearing is because of the
prohibition of an animal carrying on שבת. Shabbos. The תורה Torah says
למען ינוח שורך וחמורך, lema'an yanuach shorecha va-chamorecha, so that your ox
and your donkey may rest. This means a person's animal is not
allowed to do מלאכה melacha on שבת. Shabbos. Carrying a משא, masa,
a burden, in the רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim is a form of
מלאכה. melacha. However, if the animal is wearing something for its own
protection or to keep it from running away, it's not a משא,
masa, it's a תכשיט, tachshit, an ornament or a piece of clothing
or necessary equipment. The גמרא Gemara in the beginning of the פרק
Perek discusses the different types of restraints. The camel needs an אפסנא.
afsana. The נאקה nakah needs a חטם. chotem. This is because some
animals need more restraint than others. If you provide more restraint than
is necessary, it might become a משא. masa. For example, if you
put a heavy halter on a small goat, it's not needed for
restraint, so it's a burden. But for a camel, it is necessary.
The גמרא Gemara explains that the אפסנא afsana is a simple rope
halter. But a חטם chotem is a ring that goes through the
nose. This is necessary for a dromedary because they are much more
difficult to lead. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and his wife רחל Rachel
chose to endure the most difficult conditions because they understood that they
were building their foundation on the תורה Torah and on learning. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wasn't always a great scholar. For many years, he
was a simple shepherd who couldn't even read the אלף בית. Alef-Bet.
One day, while he was out with his sheep, he saw a
stone that had a deep hole carved into it. He asked, "Who
hollowed out this stone?" And they told him, "The water that drips
on it every single day." רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva realized that if
soft water can pierce a hard stone through persistence, then the words
of the תורה, Torah, which are as hard as iron, can certainly
penetrate my heart. At the age of forty, he went to the
schoolhouse with his young son and they began to learn the אלף
בית Alef-Bet together. He spent the next twenty-four years studying until he
became the leader of tens of thousands of תלמידים. talmidim. When he
finally returned home, he told his students that all of his תורה
Torah knowledge was only thanks to his wife, רחל. Rachel. He said,
"שלי ושלכם שלה הוא," Sheli v'shelachem shela hu, everything that I have
and everything that you have belongs to her. The רמב"ם Rambam in
ספר המצוות. Sefer Hamitzvos. Let's find it here. The רמב"ם Rambam says,
let's see here, the רמב"ם Rambam says in שורש ט'. Shoresh Tes.
Wait. One second. He says in שורש ט' Shoresh Tes that we
don't count מצוות Mitzvos that are הוראת שעה. Horoas Sho'oh. What is
הוראת שעה? Horoas Sho'oh? Something that was said only for a time.
The first thing is we see by יוסף Yosef that the פסוק
Pasuk calls him a נער, Na'ar, as a young boy. And the
פסוק Pasuk says, והוא נער את בני בלהה ואת בני זלפה. V'hu
na'ar et bnei Bilhah v'et bnei Zilpah. What was this נער Na'ar
business? רש״י Rashi explains he used to do נערות, Na'arut, he used
to fix his eyes, he used to fix his hair, he used
to act like a young boy. And the question is, what was
a צדיק Tzaddik like יוסף Yosef doing fixing his hair, making sure
his eyes looked good? He's in the middle of being a slave!
His father's mourning him! What is he doing? But the answer is,
יוסף Yosef understood that in order to survive the situation, he had
to have שמחה. Simcha. He had to have a certain sense of
self-worth. If he would have just let himself go, if he would
have become depressed, if he would have become a person that just
didn't care about anything, he would have never been able to survive
the נסיון Nisayon of אשת פוטיפר, Eshet Potiphar, he would have never
been able to become the king of מצרים. Mitzrayim. He had to
keep himself together. He had to have that sense of I'm a
בן מלך, Ben Melech, I'm a son of יעקב אבינו, Yaakov Avinu,
I'm important. And that's why he was doing those actions of a
נער. Na'ar. It wasn't because he was a בעל גאווה, Baal Ga'avah,
it wasn't because he was into himself. It was a tool to
keep himself going, to keep himself happy, to keep himself with a
sense of dignity. And that's a lesson for us. Sometimes we're in
a difficult situation. We're in a bit of a גלות. Golus. We
have to make sure to keep our heads high, to remember that
we are children of the king, to have that שמחה, Simcha, because
that שמחה Simcha is the only way we can overcome the challenges
that we face. And this is also the connection
to חנוכה. Chanukah. The Greeks wanted to take
away our identity, they wanted to take
away our self-worth, they wanted us to
feel like we're just like everyone else.
And the חשמונאים Chashmonaim said no, we are
קדוש, Kadosh, we are special, we have a
connection to the רבונו של עולם. Ribbono Shel Olam. And
that's what we celebrate on חנוכה, Chanukah, that
sense of identity and that sense of
שמחה. Simcha. So wishing everyone a פרייליכן חנוכה
Freilichen Chanukah and a גוט שבת. Gut Shabbos. And
the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah says the reason for
this is because when we stand before
הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu in judgement, we want
to show him that we are taking
our מצוות Mitzvos seriously and we're willing to
take on a חומרא Chumra to show our
sincerity in our תשובה. Teshuva. Even though all
year long a person may be lenient
and rely on those who permit פת
פלטר, Pas Paltar, the bread of a non-Jewish baker,
during these עשרת ימי תשובה, Aseres Yemei Teshuva, we try to be
more careful to only eat פת ישראל. Pas Yisroel. It's a way
of showing השם Hashem that we
are
making
an
effort
to
be
better,
to
be
more
holy,
and
to
be
more
careful
with
the
way
we
live
our
lives.
This
is
a
very
important
יסוד
Yesod
in
the
עבודת
השם
Avodas
Hashem
of
these
days.
We
want
to
show
that
our
תשובה
Teshuva
is
sincere
and
that
we
are
willing
to
go
above
and
beyond
the
basic
requirement
of
the
הלכה
Halacha
in
order
to
find
more
חן
Chen
in
the
eyes
of
the
רבונו
של
עולם.
Ribono
Shel
Olam.